Now that we've done that, we have the first component.
Let's go ahead and let you all play around with creating
your own components from your app.
So the exercise here is to basically go inside of your
forum app, so whether it's the office or community or
whatever, and then look at your index.html file and go, OK,
I want to create some components out of this.
How will I do it?
And to give some preface as well, you will run into a
limitation pretty quickly as far as things that you'll want
to do with it.
But I want to just get you in the practice of creating some
.view files, and just know that it'll functionally be
broken until we get back together.
But I just want to get you all in the
habit of practicing that.
Does that sound good?
So you basically try scoping, like bringing stuff
together, and seeing how that goes.
OK, welcome back, everyone.
So hopefully you all had some fun creating components.
But I was kind of walking around and checking out how
people were doing.
You probably ran into a problem, basically, as you
started migrating stuff, because a lot of your code is
dependent on one another.
And so you might have noticed that when you started moving
stuff that it was like, wait, where's this thing you
reference to, and had trouble talking to each other.
So let's go ahead and show you what I mean by that.
So let me start by opening up my app.view for my avatar
las airbender.
And so as we can see here, we have a couple sections here
that could really make sense.
We see a bunch of h2s.
They could make sense as components, to be totally
honest, as far as these are the characters.
This is the character list.
And so let's actually try something as simple as that.
Let's go ahead and start by inside of our components.
Let's create a character list.view.
OK, and I'm going to bring this over.
And then we have our script block that we're going to have.
And we're going to have our template block.
This time, I'm going to flip it a bit.
And we're going to start by bringing over all the HTML.
So the h2 up until this point is all to do with the
characters.
So if you save that, a lot of stuff is going to be missing,
but that's totally fine.
And let's just save placeholder for character list.
And then up here, this is where it gets a little bit
tricky now.
OK, what do we want to do?
Well, we know that character list here is relevant.
So let's start by exporting a default object, because this
is the object that defines our app.
So character list is here.
Great.
Let's do that.
So I need my data property.
And then I can put my character list in here.
Awesome.
And then let's see.
What else do we got?
Well, we have that.
Yep, length.
This looks pretty good.
Actually, this looks pretty good.
Oh, actually here.
We have a favorite character.
OK.
How do we do that?
Let's see.
Let's go here.
Yes, we have a method here for favorite character.
So I'm just going to copy the whole block knowing that I
would delete the add new character.
And this is probably what you started doing.
And then you're like, oh, yes.
There's also the this.favoriteList.
And then we're like, OK, let's add that to here.
FavoriteList.
And then we save.
And then you're thinking, OK, great.
I'm going to import character list from components.characterList.view.
OK.
That's that.
And then you're like, I'm going to register my component
at characterList.
Just like that.
And then, whoops, this needs to be renamed properly.
And then you probably came in and was like, OK,
I'm going to try to call my character list component
inside of here.
Now, if we take a look at what's happening here,
let me go ahead and close this.
And then we're going to go ahead and get out of this,
go over to our atla forum, run that dev, great.
You're probably going to realize very shortly
that nothing is working.
Anyone have any guesses as to why nothing is working?
Because your parent app relies on the character list
for the bender statistics.
OK.
So as we can see here, we actually
are relying on inside of app.view.
Sorry, I technically moved this at this point.
We're actually trying to reference this characterList
property, but you'll notice it's gone.
And this is what I was mentioning earlier.
When you have components, the data's
are scoped to the component.
It's not scoped to the entire app.
So in other words, this whole characterList component,
which I made based on impulse, actually,
if we think about Dataflow, it's the wrong way.
Because the characterList is actually basically at the top.
That's the thing that serves everything else.
So let's rethink that over again.
Because what we really want is the ability
to have the app pushed down into a child's components.
Single direction Dataflow is a very big topic these days.
Because it helps to basically ensure
that things are easier to track.
I know that was one of the initial blowbacks
when it came to two-way binding, is
that people were confused about which way data was flowing.
But that doesn't make two-way data binding
like wrong in and of itself.
We can see that when it's done in an encapsulated way,
that's easy to understand.
It's great.
But when it comes to long data flows,
we found as an industry that unidirectional Dataflow,
basically from top down, is keeping that consistent,
for the most part, has been very helpful for making things
maintainable and easier to basically work on.
OK.
So actually, what I've done here as an exercise
is an exercise in futility.
So I'm going to go ahead and clear these changes.
And we're going to go ahead and take
a look how we should be thinking about character
like componentizing our app.
So I can go ahead and delete this.
And then we can refresh the app now.
OK, everything should be working.
Oh, I think I made everything crash.
OK, refresh.
OK, everything's good.
OK.
So the way to think about components
is really the component tree.
Again, your app.view is at the very top.
Everything else goes down from that.
So let's pick something smaller to refactor
to kind of show you what I mean.
The easiest thing for here, it looks like,
is actually probably the statistics module
that we had just built.
Because really, it has the one computed property here.
And then after that, that's basically it.
There's not really any other dependencies.
So this is a nice small encapsulated one
that we can practice on.
So here, I'll tell it vendorstatistics.view.
And this time, I'll blow it up to the side
since we're not worried about how it looks right now.
And so what we want to go ahead and do
is go ahead and see what that looks like.
So first, I'm going to grab the template.
There we go.
And the template is this short block.
It's just this H2 statistics.
And as well, we're going to loop through and find
this vendorstatistics.
So now we need that data property, script.
And the data property we're looking for here
is vendorstatistics here.
And it looks like this is the only computed property
in this entire app.
So we can actually just cut the whole thing.
And we can export our default object
and paste in our computed property, which is great.
Now, this is feeling better.
However, as you mentioned before, we still have a block
in that if we go ahead and open this up inside of VIT right
now, so if I save, you'll notice that one, it's fine.
The vendor statistic doesn't show up.
No errors.
And that's to be expected because, well, we're not
calling anything.
But when we import vendor statistics,
and so that was an autocomplete, by the way, no magic there,
just it's reading it.
There we go.
We can register it.
So components, vendor, statistics.
And then we can try to call it by rendering it out here.
OK, boom.
Big error.
Why?
Because if we look inside of the four each,
what's it looking for?
It's looking for characterless.
It doesn't exist.
So now we've proven both ways that data just doesn't magically
get scoped out.
And again, this is a good thing because you want things
to inherently be scoped to the context in which they're in.